A Guide to the Major William Henry Johnson Papers (1858-1935) 1884-1935
Johnston Memorial Library, Virginia State University
Special Collections and Archives, Johnston Memorial Library, Virginia State University
Major William Henry Johnson Papers 1884-1935
Special Collections and Archives, Johnston Memorial Library, Virginia State University
1957-3
The William Henry Johnson papers include correspondence, speeches, photographs and other documents. They reflect William Henry Johnson's life as an educator, soldier and community leader.
Administrative Information
Access
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
The papers of Major William Henry Johnson were given to Virginia State University around 1957.
Biographical/Historical Information
In 1935 the highest-ranking black officer in the disbanded 6th Virginia Volunteer Infantry, Spanish American War, died. Few Virginians have ever heard of the 6th Virginia, let alone their commander, Major William Henry Johnson.
His story is unique, also, because he was one of the most successful post-bellum blacks in Petersburg who was not a descendant of the antebellum free black population. (There were around 3,200 free blacks in 1860). Major Johnson was from the slave population (which numbered around 5,000 in 1860). Free blacks had a slight advantage over the larger slave population, although they themselves were not truly free. They did have a bit more freedom of movement than their slave brethren did. In addition, some had some property that could be sold or borrowed upon to finance to own or accumulate property; therefore at emancipation they were truly penniless.
Major Johnson's father, Henry Johnson, was born a slave around 1835 in Ettrick on Fleets Farm, what is now Virginia State University, and he grew up in the old plantation house. He remained a slave until the Union Army moved through Ettrick following Robert E. Lee in April of 1865.
William Henry Johnson's mother, Malinda, was also a slave; she resided in Petersburg. October 1, 1858, her only child was born on Old Street (which is now Grove Avenue). In fact, in 1865 when Ulysses S. Grant entered Petersburg, her owner, Major P. Branch, fled to Danville taking Malinda and her six-year old son with him. William Henry's early years were spent in several places in Petersburg. At one time he lived on Old Street near Market, opposite Dunlop's Tobacco Factory. Another home was on the site of the old Titus Foundry. He also lived for some time on High Street and South Sycamore Street.
After General Lee's surrender, his mother and father were reunited. Later in the year his father brought a piece of property in the old field area in the vicinity of what is now Rome Street. Here his father built a small house, which is still standing, at what is now 1151 Rome Street. The family moved in at Christmas 1865.
Henry Johnson for 45 years was a teamster, driving his own horse and wagon. For a brief time he was a partner in an oyster house near the corner of Union and Oak Streets.
Then, as today, many blacks connected upward mobility with one's level of education. William Henry Johnson's parents were of that opinion and began his schooling at home. His first teacher, other than his mother, was a Mrs. Addie Berry who taught school at her home on Perry Street. Next, was Mr. Collier Tabb who taught school at "East Hill" on Lombard Street. His next mover was to the basement of the Gillfield Baptist Church under a Mr. Bates. After spending some time there he was enrolled in another private school. A former Confederate Army officer, Major Giles B. Cooke, taught this one. This school was located in the same building as the old First Baptist church near Garrison and Filmore Streets. He was graduated in 1874 (the first graduating class).
During the summer and early fall months when school was not in session, William Henry prepared for a trade. He chose to become a cooper (one who makes barrels). He secured summer employment at a barrel company in Richmond where he remained for two summers. Here he learned the early stages of barrel construction, called "slack work". Upon mastering "slack work" he apprenticed himself to a Mr. Wilson Goodwyn who had a shop on Union Street, to learn "tight work". During the next two years (1874-1886) he became a master cooper, making barrels for Myers Whiskey Distillery in Blandford, flour and hogshead and tierces for Ropers Tobacco Factory on Halifax Street.
After he completed his apprenticeship, his mother and father decided that he should go to college. The three of them met with Rev. Mr. Henry Williams, their pastor, and together agreed upon Hampton Normal and Industrial Institute. Despite the necessity of constant employment, after two years of study he was graduated from Hampton with a normal degree in 1878. In addition to his degree he also attended several summer teaching institutes at what is now Virginia State University.
After graduating from Hampton, Johnson returned home to Petersburg and began trying to locate a teaching position. That October he was offered a position in Surry County, about three miles from the courthouse. His new job involved teaching night school and paid $20 per month plus room and board and lodging. His students were both young and old, eager to learn, and he was an enthusiastic teacher.
He worked in Surry for five months. Later the following fall, quite by chance, on a walk through lower Chesterfield County he encountered a Captain Blankenship who was the County School Superintendent. A conference was held and the superintendent then offered a position at a new school that was under construction near what is now Virginia State University. He accepted the position and taught at that school, which was later called the "Old Brickyard School" on Dupuy Road in Ettrick.
Major Johnson taught at this school for seven years, seven months a year at $30 per month. In 1886 he was offered the principalship of Lombard Street School in Petersburg, with a nine-month school year and a record-breaking wage of $40 per month. He accepted right away. This was not just a raise of $150 per year, this also made it possible for him to give up making barrels in the evenings from March through August. This job as a cooper paid $3 - $4 per day and was used to supplement his teaching salary. He remained at Lombard Street School for two years until a new position at the Jones Street School was offered and accepted. Here he remained as principal for 31 years until the building was razed and the new Peabody-Williams Building was erected as a combination elementary and high school in 1919. He opposed this combined school because he felt the two levels should be in separate buildings. Nevertheless, he became principal of the elementary division until he retired in 1929. After 43 years of teaching in the city of Petersburg and more than 50 years in the state of Virginia.
In 1887 William Henry Johnson married Miss Nannie Brewer. The new Mrs. Johnson was the daughter of Mr. and Mrs. John Brewer, who were very highly respected citizens of Petersburg. Mr. John Brewer's father was born a slave and belonged to James Nicholas. As a slave, Mr. Brewer was allowed to "hire out," that is, he was allowed to engage in some type of extra work where a part of the money went to the owner and the rest was pocketed by the slave. By late 1864, Brewer had managed to pay his owner a $1000 and was allowed to purchase himself from his owner. His self-purchase was within four months of the end of the Confederacy when all slaves were automatically free. In the early years, he was a painter. Later he owned and operated on of the most popular restaurants in Petersburg. His place was located at 10 Bank Street.
Nannie Brewer Johnson was educated in Petersburg and attended the 1888 Normal for Teachers, an institute held at what is now Virginia State University. Mrs. Johnson was active in community and church work. She was a faithful member of Gillfield Baptist Church. Major and Mrs. Johnson were married for 48 years.
During the era of black slavery, one of the greater fears of the white community was that of an armed rebellion of blacks. When the Civil War began, many free blacks in the south volunteered to take up arms for the Confederacy. This was true even in Petersburg. However, the state of Virginia was not prepared to accept armed black men, even volunteers. This policy remained until 1871 when Virginia reorganized the state Militia and allowed the formation of volunteer companies black and white.
The first black volunteer company in Petersburg came into existence in June of 1873. They were the Petersburg Guards, organized and captained by John H. Hill. For five years the Guards were the only black volunteer company in Petersburg. In 1878, however, Lieutenant Peyton L. Farley of the Guards resigned and organized the Petersburg Blues, which he also captained. William Henry Johnson joined the Blues in 1878 as a private. The Blues began complying a notable record in competition with other companies throughout the state. In 1881 they were invited to participate in the inaugural parade of President James A. Garfield. In 1888 Johnson, now a captain, led the Blues on a very successful trip to Providence, Long Island, and Boston, Massachusetts. Between the years 1888-1897, Captain Johnson became Major Johnson and assumed command of the 2nd Battalion, Virginia Volunteer Infantry. In 1897 the Ulysses S. Grant Monument Parade was held in New York City and both the first and second Battalions made a fine showing for themselves and the state.
When war with Spain was declared in 1898, the two black battalions were federalized and became the 6th Virginia U.S. Volunteer Army of the Spanish American War. The men met and voted to serve anywhere they were sent and elected to serve under their own officers. When this reached the press, an uproar evolved over the latter statement. Some whites opposed the idea of black officers. The unit, nevertheless, moved to a training camp at Camp Poland near Knoxville, Tennessee. There, a rumor concerning the ouster of all black officers were proven to be true.
All black officers were ordered to take an exam to determine whether they would be allowed to keep their ranks. The black officers declared that they had all taken exams before training their ranks, and what if those exams were good enough then, they should be good enough now. When the second order was given, nine black officers resigned. White officers were immediately selected to fill the vacancies. The men of the 6th Virginia were very upset. Their former black officers asked them to go on without them. The war, however, ended so quickly that the men from Virginia never saw service in Cuba or the Philippines. The unit was discharged in Georgia in 1899. Virginia disbanded the black Volunteer companies and would not accept black again in the State National Guard for many years. Major Johnson continued to try and convince the governors of the state to allow the reformation of the black militia companies, but with no success.
Aside from a purely military function the black companies also served as social organs for the black community. Socials and picnics were held and enjoyed by all. The wives and sweethearts of the men formed various auxiliaries and took it upon themselves to help raise funds and to purchase such items as ceremonial swords and flags.
Major William Henry Johnson and his wife were members of the Gillfield Baptist Church, which has been located on Perry Street since 1815. He had been associated with the church since birth and was baptized in the year 1886. When the Rev. Mr. Henry Williams died in 1900 he became superintendent of the Gillfield Baptist Church Sunday School. He also served as church clerk and financial secretary, was a vice-president of the home mission and president of the Gillfield Baptist Church Temperance Society. He served the Bethany Baptist Sunday School Convention as president for twenty-five years and recording secretary for five years.
Although William Henry spent a considerable amount of time in other activities, he still found time to become involved with different groups around the city and state. He was vice-president of the Negro Organizational Society, which was founded in 1912 at Hampton Institute. This was and organization dedicated to the improvement of health, education and agriculture amongst black people. Johnson was one of the founders of a black Chamber of Commerce in Petersburg and served as their president in 1924. In 1925 he was elected vice-president of the Old Dominion Investment Company, a black local bank, and he was connected with the Ideal Investment Company and Realty Corporation of Virginia, also a local black banking concern.
Last but not least, he was one of the first black feature writers for a white southern newspaper. In 1919 the Petersburg Progress-Index engaged him to write a serious column about black life in the city. The column appeared first as "Rome Street" and was then renamed "Subjects of Interest to Colored Readers." It lasted for 16 years, until 1935.
Scope and Content Information
The papers of Major William Henry Johnson were given to Virginia State University around 1957. They reflect the accomplishments of a person born a slave of slave parents in an uncertain time. There is personal and business correspondence dating from 1884. Hundreds of photographs show the black population in and around Petersburg frozen in time, leaving us a vivid picture of what they considered important in their lives. Perhaps the most outstanding series of papers is that which concern most of his speeches and writings. These cover a variety of topics and gives us an idea of what the black elite thought about their own lives an how they viewed the issues of their day.
The Johnson papers are one of the most interesting bodies of papers left by a post-bellum black of this time period. They are a true reflection of a time now gone. These, and other items such as these, will help us to understand more about this time and the often-neglected role by blacks.
Series Description
Series I: Correspondence: Family, Personal, Business, and Military
Container: 1
Container: 2
Letters, postcards and telegrams arranged chronologically. 1884-1935
Series II: Financial and legal
Container: 3
Teaching contracts, receipts, agreements, certificates, and military discharge. Arranged by type
Series III: Speeches and Writings
Containers: 4-7
Four boxes of handwritten and several printed speeches and articles. Included is an autobiography. A list of Publications.
Series IV: Photographs
Containers: 8-14
Seven boxes, family, friends work and church scenes. In box 12 are the photos of the 6th Virginia United States Colored Volunteers.
Series V: Printed (Memorabilia)
Container: 15
Announcements, Commencement programs, Broadsides, Programs, Invitations, Pamphlets. Two very interesting items: A Restaurant Menu from his father-in-law's business on Bank Street, and the first invitation to the "Ugly Club" 1886.
Series VI: Scrapbooks
Containers: 16-19
Some of everything. Programs, cards, photographs and some correspondence.
Series VII: Artifacts
Containers: 20-25
Household articles, toys and games. Two boxes of military items. There are also two military footlockers and the sheath for a dress saber.
Series VIII: Oversize
Container:
Maps and Photos
Other Descriptive Data
William Henry Johnson authored the following books:
A History of Gillfield Baptist Church
A Glimpse of The Happenings of the Gillfield Baptist Sabbath School-1928
History of the Colored Volunteer Infantry of Virginia 1871-99 - 1923
Contents List
- Major William Henry Johnson Papers 1884-1935 (Box-folder 2:35)
  - Correspondence: Family, Personal, Business, and Military 1884 (Box-folder 1:1)
  - Correspondence 1886 (Box-folder 1:2)
  - Correspondence 1906-1909 (Box-folder 1:3)
  - Correspondence 1910 (Box-folder 1:4)
  - Correspondence 1911 (Box-folder 1:5)
  - Correspondence 1912-1913 (Box-folder 1:6)
  - Correspondence 1914 (Box-folder 1:7)
  - Correspondence 1915 (Box-folder 1:8)
  - Correspondence 1916 (Box-folder 1:9)
  - Correspondence 1917 (Box-folder 1:10)
  - Correspondence 1918 (Box-folder 1:11)
  - Correspondence 1919 (Box-folder 1:12)
  - Correspondence 1920 (Box-folder 1:13)
  - Correspondence 1921 (Box-folder 1:14)
  - Correspondence 1922 (Box-folder 1:15)
  - Correspondence 1923 (Box-folder 1:16)
  - Correspondence 1924 (Box-folder 1:17)
  - Correspondence 1925 (Box-folder 1:18)
  - Correspondence 1926 (Box-folder 1:19)
  - Correspondence 1927 (Box-folder 1:20)
  - Correspondence 1929-1931 (Box-folder 1:21)
  - Correspondence 1933-1935 (Box-folder 1:22)
  - Correspondence n.d. (Box-folder 1:23)
  - Correspondence Military 1886-1888 (Box-folder 2:24)
  - Correspondence Military 1898-1899 (Box-folder 2:26)
  - Correspondence Military 1917-1919 (Box-folder 2:27)
  - Correspondence Military 1920-1921 (Box-folder 2:28)
  - Correspondence Military 1922-1926 (Box-folder 2:29)
  - Correspondence Military 1931 (Box-folder 2:30)
  - Military Receipts-Pay 1898 (Box-folder 2:31)
  - Military Receipts 1896-1898 (Box-folder 2:32)
  - Army Discharge 1898 (Box-folder 2:33)
  - Unit Patch 6th USCT n.d. (Box-folder 2:34)
  - Tickets n.d. (Box-folder 2:35)
- Financial and legal 1901-1920, n.d. (Box-folder 1:5)
  - Register of Copyright 1901 (Box-folder 3:36)
  - Public School contracts, Pension information 1912-1920 (Box-folder 3:37)
  - Stocks and Bonds n.d. (Box-folder 3:38)
  - Receipts General n.d. (Box-folder 3:39)
  - Receipts General n.d. (Box-folder 3:40)
- Speeches and Writings 1884-1928 (Box-folder 4:119)
  - Industrial Education 1884 (Box-folder 4:41)
  - Discipline 1911 (Box-folder 4:42)
  - Our Condition Generally 1912 (Box-folder 4:43)
  - Founders Day Address 1926 (Box-folder 4:44)
  - The Source of Lasting Power 1928 (Box-folder 4:45)
  - Sister Jordan n.d. (Box-folder 4:46)
  - Discipline n.d. (Box-folder 4:47)
  - 48. School Thought (Box-folder 4:48)
  - Discipline (Box-folder 4:49)
  - Relative Efficiency of Infantry and Calvary (Box-folder 4:50)
  - Vigilantism (Box-folder 4:51)
  - Influence (Box-folder 4:52)
  - Attendance (Box-folder 4:53)
  - 54. Sunday School Work (Box-folder 4:54)
  - 55. The Attitude of the Sunday School to the Community (Box-folder 4:55)
  - Why an Association of this kind is needed (Box-folder 4:56)
  - The Influence of the Sabbath School (Box-folder 4:57)
  - The Public School System of Virginia and What it Means to U.S. (Box-folder 4:57a)
  - No title 1888 (Box-folder 4:58)
  - No title 1897 (Box-folder 4:59)
  - No title 1897 (Box-folder 4:60)
  - No title 1911 (Box-folder 4:61)
  - No title 1911 (Box-folder 4:62)
  - No title 1911 (Box-folder 4:62a)
  - No title 1912 (Box-folder 4:63)
  - No title 1914 (Box-folder 4:63)
  - No title 1914 (Box-folder 4:65)
  - No title 1915 (Box-folder 4:66)
  - No title 1916 (Box-folder 4:67)
  - No title 1917 (Box-folder 4:67a)
  - No title 1918 (Box-folder 4:68)
  - No title 1922 (Box-folder 4:69)
  - No title 1923 (Box-folder 4:70)
  - No title 1923 (Box-folder 4:71)
  - No title 1923 (Box-folder 4:72)
  - No title 1925 (Box-folder 4:73)
  - No title 1928 (Box-folder 4:74)
  - At Gillfield n. d. n. t. (Box-folder 5:75)
  - At Gillfield n.d.n.t (Box-folder 5:76)
  - At Gillfield n.d.n.t (Box-folder 5:76)
  - At Gillfield n.d.n.t (Box-folder 5:77)
  - At Gillfield n.d.n.t (Box-folder 5:78)
  - At Gillfield n.d.n.t (Box-folder 5:79)
  - At Gillfield n.d.n.t (Box-folder 5:80)
  - At Gillfield n.d.n.t (Box-folder 5:81)
  - At Gillfield n.d.n.t (Box-folder 5:82)
  - At Gillfield n.d.n.t (Box-folder 5:83)
  - At Gillfield n.d.n.t (Box-folder 5:84)
  - At Gillfield n.d.n.t (Box-folder 5:85)
  - At Gillfield n.d.n.t (Box-folder 5:86)
  - At Virginia State University n.d.n.t (Box-folder 5:87)
  - At Virginia State University n.d.n.t (Box-folder 5:87a)
  - At Virginia State University n.d.n.t (Box-folder 5:88)
  - At Virginia State University n.d.n.t (Box-folder 5:89)
  - At Virginia State University n.d.n.t (Box-folder 5:90)
  - At Virginia State University (VN & CI) n.d.n.t (Box-folder 5:91)
  - At Virginia State University (VN & CI) n.d.n.t (Box-folder 5:92)
  - At Virginia State University (VN & CI) n.d.n.t (Box-folder 5:93)
  - At Virginia State University (VN & CI) n.d.n.t (Box-folder 5:94)
  - The Order of St. Luke n.d.n.t (Box-folder 5:95)
  - The Virginia State Sabbath School Convention n.d.n.t (Box-folder 5:96)
  - The Virginia State Sabbath School Convention n.d.n.t (Box-folder 5:97)
  - The Virginia State Sabbath School Convention n.d.n.t (Box-folder 5:98)
  - The Virginia State Sabbath School Convention n.d.n.t (Box-folder 5:99)
  - At The State Sunday School Convention n.d.n.t (Box-folder 5:100)
  - Before the Sunday School Union n.d.n.t (Box-folder 5:101)
  - Before the Bethany Baptist Sunday School n.d.n.t (Box-folder 5:102)
  - Before the Bethany Baptist Sunday School n.d.n.t (Box-folder 5:103)
  - Before the Bethany Baptist Sunday School n.d.n.t (Box-folder 5:104)
  - Before the Bethany Baptist Sunday School n.d.n.t (Box-folder 5:105)
  - Before the Bethany Baptist Sunday School n.d.n.t (Box-folder 5:106)
  - At the YMCA n.d.n.t (Box-folder 5:107)
  - Before Dinwidde Farmers Conference n.d.n.t (Box-folder 5:108)
  - Before the Temperance Society n.d.n.t (Box-folder 5:109)
  - Before the Knights of Pythias n.d.n.t (Box-folder 5:110)
  - Before Petersburg Teachers n.d.n.t (Box-folder 5:111)
  - Before Petersburg Teachers n.d.n.t (Box-folder 5:112)
  - At Zion Baptist-Petersburg n.d.n.t (Box-folder 5:113)
  - At Zion Baptist-Petersburg n.d.n.t (Box-folder 5:114)
  - About Anne Blackwell n.d.n.t (Box-folder 6:115)
  - About Bethany Baptist n.d.n.t (Box-folder 6:116)
  - About Bishop Payne's School n.d.n.t (Box-folder 6:117)
  - About Bishop Payne's School n.d.n.t (Box-folder 6:118)
  - About the Boys Scouts n.d.n.t (Box-folder 6:119)
  - About Dellia Hayden n.d.n.t (Box-folder 6:120)
  - About Dellia Hayden n.d.n.t (Box-folder 6:121)
  - About the Elks n.d.n.t (Box-folder 6:122)
  - About Gillfield Sabbath School n.d.n.t (Reel 6:123)
  - About John H. Lamb n.d.n.t (Box-folder 6:124)
  - Before the Ladies Auxiliary n.d.n.t (Box-folder 6:125)
  - About St. Lukes/Mary Prout n.d.n.t (Box-folder 6:126)
  - Before the Mothers League n.d.n.t (Box-folder 6:127)
  - About the Peoples Cemetery n.d.n.t (Box-folder 6:128)
  - About Sabbath Schools n.d.n.t (Box-folder 6:129)
  - About Temperance n.d.n.t (Box-folder 6:130)
  - About Rev. Henry Williams n.d.n.t (Box-folder 6:131)
  - 132. Before the City of Petersburg about Henry Williams n.d.n.t (Box-folder 6:132)
  - n.t. n.d. (Box-folder 6:133)
  - n.t. n.d. (Box-folder 6:134)
  - n.t. n.d. (Box-folder 6:135)
  - n.t. n.d. (Box-folder 6:136)
  - n.t. n.d. (Box-folder 6:137)
  - n.t. n.d. (Box-folder 6:138)
  - n.t. n.d. (Box-folder 6:139)
  - n.t. n.d. (Box-folder 6:140)
  - n.t. n.d. (Box-folder 6:141)
  - n.t. n.d. (Box-folder 6:142)
  - n.t. n.d. (Box-folder 6:143)
  - n.t. n.d. (Box-folder 6:144)
  - n.t. n.d. (Box-folder 6:145)
  - n.t. n.d. (Box-folder 6:146)
  - n.t. n.d. (Box-folder 6:147)
  - n.t. n.d. (Box-folder 6:148)
  - n.t. n.d. (Box-folder 6:149)
  - n.t. n.d. (Box-folder 6:150)
  - n.t. n.d. (Box-folder 6:151)
  - n.t. n.d. (Box-folder 6:152)
  - n.t. n.d. (Box-folder 6:153)
  - n.t. n.d. (Box-folder 6:154)
  - n.t. n.d. (Box-folder 6:155)
  - n.t. n.d. (Box-folder 7:156)
  - n.t. n.d. (Box-folder 7:157)
  - n.t. n.d. (Box-folder 7:158)
  - n.t. n.d. (Box-folder 7:159)
  - n.t. n.d. (Box-folder 7:160)
- Speeches and Writings (Box-folder 1:17)
  - Writing/Manuscript (Box-folder 7:161)
  - Writing (Box-folder 7:162)
  - Report (Box-folder 7:163)
  - Writing (Box-folder 7:164)
  - Writing/Manuscript (Box-folder 7:165)
  - Writing (Box-folder 7:166)
  - Autobiography (Box-folder 7:167)
  - Autobiography (Box-folder 7:168)